<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An antidote of rare physick. No rarer thing that you can find, to cure a discontented mind; a contented mind it is most rare, if you serve the Lord and stand in fear: and let no want nor poverty, disquiet your mind, I tell to ye; for God hath all things still in store, if you have content you need no more The tune is, No love like a contented mind: or, Phancies Phenix.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01419</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3497</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide EBB65H[7]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.10[1]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99887031</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99887031</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181757</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01419)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181757)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A2:3[7]; A6:2[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An antidote of rare physick. No rarer thing that you can find, to cure a discontented mind; a contented mind it is most rare, if you serve the Lord and stand in fear: and let no want nor poverty, disquiet your mind, I tell to ye; for God hath all things still in store, if you have content you need no more The tune is, No love like a contented mind: or, Phancies Phenix.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.) : ill. (woodcuts).  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Deacon, at the Angel in Guiltsput street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "Indeed this world is so unjust ..."</note>
                  <note>Place, date of publication, and publisher's name from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: copy trimmed, affecting imprint; item at A6:2 stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the British Library and Harvard University, Houghton Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ballads, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:181757:1"/>
            <head>An Antidote of Rare Phyſick.</head>
            <argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>No Rarer thing that you can find,</l>
                  <l>To Cure a Diſcontented mind;</l>
                  <l>A contented mind it is moſt rare,</l>
                  <l>If you ſerve the Lord and ſtand in fear:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And let no want nor Poverty,</l>
                  <l>Diſquiet your mind, I tell to ye;</l>
                  <l>For God hath all things ſtill in ſtore,</l>
                  <l>If you have content you need no more</l>
               </lg>
            </argument>
            <opener>The Tune is, No love like a contented mind: or, Phancies Phenix.</opener>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>INdeed this world is ſo unjuſt,</l>
               <l>Men cannot one another truſt;</l>
               <l>Some are ſo troubled in their mind,</l>
               <l>One ſcarcely now a friend can find:</l>
               <l>There is ſuch wavering every way,</l>
               <l>Makes many a man ſtand at a ſtay:</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>A contented mind it is moſt rare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If we ſerve the Lord and ſtand in fear.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If a man be poor and have but ſmall,</l>
               <l>If he be content it's the beſt of all;</l>
               <l>There's ſome has Thouſands at command,</l>
               <l>That's not content I underſtand;</l>
               <l>They pinch and ſpare to make it more,</l>
               <l>And grind the faces of the poor:</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>A contented mind, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If ſickneſs comes count that no loſs,</l>
               <l>But be content then with thy Croſs:</l>
               <l>If it be Gods will it muſt be ſo,</l>
               <l>It's a Bleſſing, pray you ſay not no:</l>
               <l>And remember <hi>Iob</hi> in all his ways,</l>
               <l>He evermore gave God the Praiſe:</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>A contented mind, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If you be caſt in Priſon never fear,</l>
               <l>Let not your heart and mind diſpair;</l>
               <l>But be content and hope the beſt,</l>
               <l>When God is pleas'd you ſhall be releas'd:</l>
               <l>That man that ſerves the God of might,</l>
               <l>If man do him wrong, God will do him right</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>A contented mind it is moſt rare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If we ſerve the Lord and ſtand in fear.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>If a man have a charge of Children ſmall,</l>
               <l>And has but little to maintain them withal,</l>
               <l>Let his prayers be ſtill unto the Lord,</l>
               <l>Then relief for them he will afford;</l>
               <l>And never murmer at your want,</l>
               <l>Although ſometimis that things be ſcant,</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>A contented mind, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Content it is a pleaſant thing therefore,</l>
               <l>And eſpecially for the Poor;</l>
               <l>If a man be brought into diſtreſs,</l>
               <l>It will relieve him in his heavineſs;</l>
               <l>And make him underſtand and ſee,</l>
               <l>What our good God can do for thee and me:</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>A contented mind, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What ever Troubles comes or goes,</l>
               <l>Let's ſerve the Lord, and give him praiſe;</l>
               <l>And keep our hearts both clear and ſound,</l>
               <l>That no evil may our conſcience wound:</l>
               <l>And love all men both Rich and Poor,</l>
               <l>And be content for evermore:</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>A contented mind, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If Maids and Young-men be tros'd in love,</l>
               <l>And neither party be unkind,</l>
               <l>Let them put their truſt in God above,</l>
               <l>And he will eaſe their troubled mind:</l>
               <l>And never pine at it I do ſay,</l>
               <l>Many has brought themſelves unto decay:</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>A contented mind, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Contents the beſt thing we can find,</l>
               <l>If any trouble do vex our mind;</l>
               <l>It will preſerve us from all evil,</l>
               <l>And expell the Poyſon of the Devil:</l>
               <l>For if our hearts be whole and ſound,</l>
               <l>No evil thing can there abound:</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>A contented mind, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That man that lives without content,</l>
               <l>And hath his heart now on Riches bent,</l>
               <l>Ne'r has enough, he'd ſtill have more,</l>
               <l>His wicked mind runs on his ſtore:</l>
               <l>But the poor man that enjoys content,</l>
               <l>Is in a better way when life is ſpent:</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>A contented mind, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Contents will cure a wounded heart,</l>
               <l>Content will never let it ſmart;</l>
               <l>Content it is a precious ſtore,</l>
               <l>And he that hath it needs no more:</l>
               <l>It's a Remedy for Rich and Poor,</l>
               <l>And a Plaſter for every wounded Sore:</l>
               <lg type="refrain">
                  <l>
                     <hi>Content it is ſo rare a thing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Great Comfort to you it will bring.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for <hi>I. Deacon,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Guiltſpur-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
